The Victor D'Amico Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- Series II. New York City High Schools Program, [1940s]-1974
  - Subseries II.A. General Background, [1940s]-1971
    - Mailings to high schools (5 of 7), 1964-1967; Includes list of exhibitions, information on school art departments, form letters (Box 2, Folder II.A.14)
    - Mailings to high schools (6 of 7), 1968-1971; Includes list of exhibitions, information on school art departments, form letters (Box 2, Folder II.A.15)
    - Mailings to high schools (7 of 7), 1971; Postcards returned from schools with information on art classes, teachers, and semester schedules (Box 2, Folder II.A.16)
    - Demonstration teaching model: design, [1946]; Photographs of box, contents: b/w prints mounted on pages previously removed from album (Box 2, Folder II.A.17)
    - Demonstration teaching model: interior design, [1946]; Photographs of box, contents: b/w prints mounted on pages previously removed from album (Box 2, Folder II.A.18)
    - Demonstration teaching model: interior design, [1946]; B/w prints (Box 2, Folder II.A.19)
    - Demonstration teaching model: neighborhood planning, [1946]; Photographs of box, contents, students using materials: b/w prints (Box 2, Folder II.A.20)
    - Demonstration teaching models, [1946]; Photographs of cabinets of materials distributed for use in classrooms: b/w glass-mounted slides (Box 3, Folder II.A.21)
    - Demonstration teaching models, [1946]; Paper-mounted color- and b/w glass-mounted slides (Box 3, Folder II.A.22)
    - Libraries of color reproductions, 1948-1952; Lists of items for Lending Library of Color Reproductions, E.P. 45A-D (Box 3, Folder II.A.23)
    - Teaching Materials for N.Y.C. Public High Schools[MoMA Exh. #412, June 7-July 20, 1949], Includes photograph of demonstration teaching model for design (see folder II.A.17): b/w prints (Box 3, Folder II.A.24)
    - You and Your Neighborhood;Modern Architecture of the Small House and City Apartment, [1949]; Photographs of exhibition panels: b/w prints (Box 3, Folder II.A.25)
    - Demonstration teaching model: costume design, [1949]; B/w prints (Box 3, Folder II.A.26)
    - Circulating exhibitions, 1949-1955; Correspondence with schools, Board of Education; includes lists of available exhibitions, participating vocational high schools (Box 3, Folder II.A.27)
    - Art for the High Schools of New York City[MoMA Exh. #720, March 19-May 20, 1963], 1949-1963; Includes reports on the High School Program, and information on previous High School Program exhibitions (Box 3, Folder II.A.28)
    - Lettering: Its Design and Arrangement;Modern Design in Furniture;Old Masters to Modern;Personality in Painting;You and Your Neighborhood, [1952-1953]; B/w prints (Box 3, Folder II.A.29)
    - Warehouse exhibition, June 1953; Photographs of exhibition of circulating educational exhibitions, displayed in their packaging: b/w prints (Box 3, Folder II.A.30)
    - D'Amico with teenage students, [1960s]; Photographs of unidentified location: b/w prints (Box 3, Folder II.A.31)
    - Educational materials, [1960s]; 11x15 panels showing works of modern art, reproduced on wallboard (Box 68, Folder II.A.32*)
    - Educational materials, [1960s]; 11x15 panels showing works of modern art, reproduced on wallboard (Box 68, Folder II.A.33*)
    - Educational materials, [1960s]; 11x15 panels showing works of modern art, reproduced on wallboard (Box 68, Folder II.A.34*)
    - Educational materials, [1960s]; "Teaching portfolio number one: Modern sculpture": text and 40 b/w plates (Box 68, Folder II.A.35*)
    - Educational materials, [1960s]; "Teaching portfolio number one: Modern sculpture": text and 40 b/w plates (Box 68, Folder II.A.36*)
    - Educational materials, [1960s]; Set of b/w plates of contemporary photography, some labeled "S1" on reverse (Box 68, Folder II.A.37*)
    - Educational materials, [1960s]; Laminated album pages of captioned op art: b/w and color (Box 68, Folder II.A.38*)
    - Educational materials, [1960s]; Album pages (lamination previously removed) of original drawings showing various art techniques, including assemblage, mobiles, and reed sculpture (Box 68, Folder II.A.39*)
    - Educational materials, [1960s]; Album pages (lamination previously removed) of original drawings showing various art techniques, including assemblage, mobiles, and reed sculpture (Box 68, Folder II.A.40*)
    - Background information, 1962, 1963, 1969, 1970; Includes 1970 summary of the program; various materials supplied (Box 3, Folder II.A.41)
    - Circulating exhibitions, 1963, 1967-1969; Correspondence with schools, intra-MoMA correspondence (Box 3, Folder II.A.42)
    - Libraries of texts, 1966-1970; Lists of books and other printed items supplied to schools as E.P. 68, 99, 111, 125, 127 (Box 3, Folder II.A.43)
    - From Collage Montage to Assemblage, 1967; List of works in MoMA’s collection; photocopied pages from publication Collage: Personalities, Concepts [and] Techniques (Box 3, Folder II.A.44)
    - Drawing the Figure, [1967]; 12" film reel; Note: This 12" film reel has been transferred to the Museum's Film Study Center, which has the proper facilities for storing and screening it. Researchers should contact the Study Center for further information. Access may be denied due to the film's physical condition. (Box 3, Folder II.A.45)
    - Loan exhibitions, [1968]; Photographs of various objects in MoMA’s collection: b/w prints (Box 3, Folder II.A.46)
  - Subseries II.B. Alphabetical List of Exhibitions and Slide Programs Distributed to Schools, 1941-1974
    Subseries II.B is a set of files received in alphabetical order by exhibition/slide set title, which have been maintained in that order here, preceded by administrative information in chronological order. They were received partly in materials from Teachers College and partly as stored at MoMA by the Department of Education. No explanations are provided for the abbreviations E.P. and V.P. in the records, but they appear to relate to exhibition and visual materials, respectively.
    The subseries includes information on educational materials, exhibitions, and slide sets that circulated to New York City public schools during and after D'Amico's tenure at MoMA, documenting the extent and range of the Program. Some exhibitions were versions of those mounted at MoMA, and some were created especially for the Program (including Modern Art of the Small House and City Apartment,Design for the Theatre,Poster Design Today,Contrasts in Painting). The materials include checklists, intra-MoMA requisitions for photographic reproductions and shipping, as well as correspondence with schools that received the materials. In folder II.B.81, High School Program Coordinator Sue Raices explains why the Program was discontinued in the early 1970s: "While exhibitions were once an important part of the program, the vastly changed school population and sometimes difficult situation in the schools have caused a shift in emphasis. Today the schools are finding more and more need for audio-visual materials."
    - Masters, Undated; List of some works in MoMA's collection: original typescript (Box 3, Folder II.B.1)
    - Materials loaned to schools, [1960s]; Detailed chart of schools to which exhibitions, teaching portfolios, and other materials traveled, with months of distribution in unidentified years (Box 69, Folder II.B.2*)
    - Correspondence with schools, meeting notes, 1970 (Box 3, Folder II.B.3)
    - List of exhibitions and numbers, 1971-1972; Includes number of pieces, dimensions, and weight (Box 3, Folder II.B.4)
    - Material no longer circulated, 1971, 1974; Annotated list of discontinued materials (Box 3, Folder II.B.5)
    - Discontinued slide talks, [1971, 1974]; Includes lists of items from What is Modern Painting?,What is Modern Sculpture?,A Century of Photography,Modern Architecture of the Modern School (Box 3, Folder II.B.6)
    - Abstract Painting, 1951-1970; E.P. 71; includes checklist, caption text from two versions of exhibition (Box 3, Folder II.B.7)
    - Adventures in Modern Art (slide set), 1970-1971; E.P. 130; checklist, text accompanying slides (Box 3, Folder II.B.8)
    - Advertising and Editorial Art, 1949, 1970; E.P. 57A, B; V.P. 3; includes checklist, caption text. Exhibition was composed of examples selected from the 28th Annual National Exhibition of Advertising and Editorial Art, sponsored by the Art Directors Club of NY and held at MoMA as Art Directors Club[MoMA Exh. #401, March 15-April 17, 1949] (Box 4, Folder II.B.9)
    - African Textiles and Decorative Arts[MoMA Exh. #1012c, October 11, 1972-January 31, 1973], Draft press release; photocopied clipping (Box 4, Folder II.B.10)
    - The Alphabet (A-Z), 1967; E.P. 124; text for one caption (Box 3, Folder II.B.11)
    - American Painting, 1947, 1950; E.P. 38A, B; includes checklist, diagrams of panels, photostats of caption text (Box 4, Folder II.B.12)
    - American Watercolors[MoMA Exh. #143, August 12-August 25, 1941], V.P. 20; includes checklist (Box 4, Folder II.B.13)
    - Art Museums in New York City, 1956-1967; E.P. 101A, B; includes caption text, photostat images, map of panel layout (Box 4, Folder II.B.14)
    - The Art of Assemblage[MoMA Exh. #695, October 4-November 12, 1961];The Responsive Eye[MoMA Exh. #757, February 25-April 25, 1965], 1968, 1970; Correspondence, order and requisition forms (Box 4, Folder II.B.15)
    - Romare Bearden: The Prevalence of Ritual[MoMA Exh. #958, March 25-June 9, 1971], 1970-1971; Includes checklist (Box 4, Folder II.B.16)
    - Cartoons of Yesterday and Today, 1962, 1963, 1970; Includes captions, transparencies and photographic prints, order and requisition forms (Box 4, Folder II.B.17)
    - Federal Art Project Changing New York, 1954; E.P. 8B; checklist (Box 4, Folder II.B.18)
    - Collection of Textiles for the Study of Dress Design, 1948, 1954; E.P. 42, 90; checklist, order and requisition forms. After the exhibition was dismantled in 1970, fabrics from it were donated to the Harlem Carnival. (Box 4, Folder II.B.19)
    - Collections of Textiles by Dan Cooper and M. Strengall; Collection of Textiles for the Study of Interior Design, 1947-1949; E.P. 41, 44; includes checklist, order and requisition forms (Box 4, Folder II.B.20)
    - Contemporary Sculpture and Constructions[MoMA Exh. #944a, November 2, 1970-February 1, 1971], 1950-1959, 1970-1971; E.P. 105A, 105B (revised 1970); includes checklist, order and requisition forms, information on a slide set "Sculpture of Our Century" (Box 4, Folder II.B.21)
    - Contrasts in Modern Painting, 1948-1952; E.P. 47A, B; includes checklist, edited caption text, order and requisition forms (Box 4, Folder II.B.22)
    - Cubism, 1972; E.P. 136A, B; includes checklist, list of New York City high school contacts, order and requisition forms (Box 4, Folder II.B.23)
    - Design for the Modern Theater, 1948; E.P. 46; includes checklist. Also has some information on "Original Costume Designs for the Modern Theater" (E.P. 14) (Box 4, Folder II.B.24)
    - Design in Lettering and Typography, 1950; E.P. 58; includes checklist, order and requisition forms (Box 4, Folder II.B.25)
    - Designing a Publication, 1951-1952; E.P. 73; includes checklist, panel text (Box 4, Folder II.B.26)
    - Designing a Textile, 1950-1951; E.P. 64; photostat labels (Box 4, Folder II.B.27)
    - 18 Posters from 10 Countries; Stages in the Making of a Poster, 1949; E.P. 55, 54; includes checklist (Box 4, Folder II.B.28)
    - Elements of the Modern House, 1965-1966; E.P. 121A, B; includes order and requisition forms (Box 4, Folder II.B.29)
    - The Fascination of Drawing, 1958-1959, 1972; E.P. 103A, B; includes checklist, transparencies of panels (Box 4, Folder II.B.30)
    - Graphic Art: Prints and Processes, Undated; E.P. 105A, B; includes checklist, caption photostats (Box 4, Folder II.B.31)
    - Graphic Design, 1970-1971; E.P. 122; includes checklist (Box 4, Folder II.B.32)
    - The Graphic Work of Ben Shahn, 1958-1959; E.P. 104A, B; panel text and transparencies, captions, panel layout (Box 4, Folder II.B.33)
    - Home Making for Moderns (slide set), 1953; E.P. 85A, B; includes description of set (Box 4, Folder II.B.34)
    - How the Artist Sees Himself, 1957-1958; E.P. 102A, B; includes panel text, transparencies (Box 4, Folder II.B.35)
    - How the Artist Sees Himself, [1957-1958]; E.P. 103: checklist (Box 4, Folder II.B.36)
    - How the Artist Sees Himself, 1971; E.P. 132A, B; checklist (Box 5, Folder II.B.37)
    - How Modern Artists Paint People[MoMA Exh. #196, September 22-October 13, 1942], 1948-1949; E.P. 39A, B; includes checklist, photostat captions (Box 5, Folder II.B.38)
    - Imagination in Architecture, 1950-1951; E.P. 60; includes checklist, label copy, order and requisition forms (Box 5, Folder II.B.39)
    - Imagination in Architecture, 1963; E.P. 116A, B: includes box list, order and requisition forms (Box 5, Folder II.B.40)
    - Introducing 10 Modern Artists, [1950]; E.P. 8A, 8B; given to Abraham Lincoln High School, Waitor High School, 1950; list of panels, panel labels (Box 5, Folder II.B.41)
    - Lettering by Hand[MoMA Exh. #714, November 6, 1962-January 6, 1963], 1962-1972; E.P. 117; includes checklists, correspondence, transfer forms, transparencies (Box 5, Folder II.B.42)
    - Lettering: Its Design and Arrangement, 1952-1953; E.P. 82: includes order and requisition forms (Box 5, Folder II.B.43)
    - Library of Framed Reproductions, before 1970; E.P. 96A, 96B; checklist; discontinued 1970 (Box 5, Folder II.B.44)
    - Library of Useful Objects, Modern Sculpture (Reference Library of Photographs), 1946-1947, 1950-1951; V.P. 7 (1950-1951), E.P. 30 (1946-1947). The latter was given to Girls High School in the fall of 1951. (Box 5, Folder II.B.45)
    - The Making of a Painting, 1952-1955; E.P. 62; previous title:How the Modern Artist Works; includes transparency, label text, correspondence (Box 5, Folder II.B.46)
    - The Making of a Sculpture, 1950-1956; E.P. 61: includes checklist, correspondence, order and requisition forms, b/w photographs with captions. Note on original folder: "The photographic panels and the box containing them were discarded on June 14, 1956" (Box 5, Folder II.B.47)
    - The Making of a Silk Screen (slide talk), 1951-1952; Includes checklist, order and requisition forms. Note on original folder: “Discarded February 1971” (Box 5, Folder II.B.48)
    - The Making of a Silk Screen Print, 1949-1950; E.P. 56, V.P. 1; includes checklist, panel text, b/w prints (Box 5, Folder II.B.49)
    - Modern American Painting, 1955; Glass-mounted color slides. These were found separately in the original folders and appear to match contents of folder II.B.51 (Box 5, Folder II.B.50)
    - Modern American Painting, Modern European Painting, 1955, 1962; E.P. 93, 94; checklists, order and requisition forms, correspondence (Box 5, Folder II.B.51)
    - Modern Architecture of the Small House and City Apartment, 1949; E.P. 49A, 49B; includes draft panel text, order and requisition forms (Box 5, Folder II.B.52)
    - Modern Art in Your Life[MoMA Exh. #423, October 5-December 4, 1949], 1949-1951; E.P. 73, V.P. 21; discontinued 1967, panels were discarded by Berkeley Express July 1970; includes panel text, label photostats, exhibition catalogue, press release (Box 5, Folder II.B.53)
    - Modern Ballet Design, 1948; E.P. 43; includes panel text, order and requisition forms (Box 5, Folder II.B.54)
    - Modern Design in Furniture, 1944-1945, 1953; E.P. 24A, 24B, 83, V.P. 22; withdrawn and dismantled July 1970. Includes checklist, panel text, correspondence (Box 5, Folder II.B.55)
    - Modern Drawings[MoMA Exh. #252, February 16-May 10, 1944], 1950, 1952; E.P. 40A, 40B; checklist (Box 5, Folder II.B.56)
    - Movie Posters, 1961; E.P. 109; includes checklist, label text (Box 5, Folder II.B.57)
    - Multiples, 1970-1972; Includes checklist, order and requisition forms, correspondence (Box 5, Folder II.B.58)
    - The New Concept of Space, 1953-1970; E.P. 86A, 86B; b/w photographs, checklist, order and requisition forms (Box 5, Folder II.B.59)
    - New Forms of Our Times, 1964-1971; E.P. 66A, 66B; includes b/w photographs, checklist, order and requisition forms (Box 5, Folder II.B.60)
    - New Forms of Our Times (slide talk);Graphic Design, [1969-1970]; E.P. 66, 122; checklists (Box 6, Folder II.B.61)
    - The New York Times Posters, 1952-1953; E.P. 77; order and requisition forms, panel text (Box 6, Folder II.B.62)
    - Objects of Everyday Use: Which Do You Like?, 1954-1955; E.P. 87A, 87B, V.P. 27; includes checklist, draft panel text, list of materials ordered (Box 6, Folder II.B.63)
    - Objects of Good Design, 1964-1965; E.P. 120A, 120B; includes packing list, panel text (Box 6, Folder II.B.64)
    - Old Masters to Modern, 1952-1953; E.P. 80; includes checklist, order and requisition forms, panel text (Box 6, Folder II.B.65)
    - Once Invisible[MoMA Exh. #833, June 20-September 11, 1967], 1971; Subtitled "The Photographer's Eye." Includes checklist, correspondence (Box 6, Folder II.B.66)
    - The Package[MoMA Exh. #647, September 9-November 1, 1959], 1961, 1972; E.P. 108; includes order and requisition forms, packing list (Box 6, Folder II.B.67)
    - Personality in Painting, 1952; E.P. 81; includes checklist, partial panel text (Box 6, Folder II.B.68)
    - Picasso in the Collection of The Museum of Modern Art[MoMA Exh. #993, February 3-April 2, 1972], E.P. 139; includes checklist, order and requisition forms, edited Acoustiguide text, press release (Box 6, Folder II.B.69)
    - Polio Poster Competition[MoMA Exh. #427, October 31-November 20, 1949], 1950-1951; This exhibition included a recorded slide talk; checklist, order and requisition forms (Box 6, Folder II.B.70)
    - Jackson Pollock, 1961-1962; E.P. 115; order and requisition forms (Box 6, Folder II.B.71)
    - Pop Art, 1966-1970; E.P. 123A; includes checklists, order and requisition forms (Box 6, Folder II.B.72)
    - Poster Boom of the 60s, 1970-1972; E.P. 129; includes checklist, mounted labels, order and requisition forms (Box 6, Folder II.B.73)
    - Poster Design Today, 1952, 1968; E.P. 48A, 48B; includes labels, checklist (Box 6, Folder II.B.74)
    - Poster Design Today, 1956-1957; E.P. 98; checklist, labels (Box 6, Folder II.B.75)
    - Science Fiction, 1969-1971; E.P. 134A, 134B; this exhibition was never completed; includes correspondence, information on science fiction films (Box 6, Folder II.B.76)
    - The Sculpture of Picasso[MoMA Exh. #841, October 11, 1967-January 1, 1968], 1970-1972; E.P. 140; correspondence, press release re: film strip created from exhibition; includes checklist (Box 6, Folder II.B.77)
    - The Sculpture of Richard Hunt[MoMA Exh. #959, March 25-June 9, 1971], 1970-1971; E.P. 135A, B; includes draft and final checklists, order and requisition forms, catalogue, panel layout (Box 6, Folder II.B.78)
    - Seeing New York, 1956-1957; E.P. 97, V.P. 30; panel labels, draft layout (Box 6, Folder II.B.79)
    - Significant Posters by Modern Artists, 1952-1953; V.P. 24; includes checklists, captions (Box 6, Folder II.B.80)
    - Small Sculptures, 1953-1958; E.P. 79; includes checklist, correspondence, panel labels (Box 6, Folder II.B.81)
    - David Smith, 1961-1965; E.P. 112; includes contents, order and requisition forms, caption text (Box 6, Folder II.B.82)
    - Ten Modern Watercolors, 1951-1953; E.P. 69A, 69B; includes checklist, order and requisition forms (Box 6, Folder II.B.83)
    - Transatlantic Cultures, 1971; E.P. 133; includes order and requisition forms (Box 6, Folder II.B.84)
    - 20th Century Design (slide set), 1972; E.P. 113A, 113; includes order and requisition forms, slide list (Box 6, Folder II.B.85)
    - 20th Century Design from the Museum Collection[MoMA Exh. #637, December 17, 1958-February 23, 1959], 1961-1973; E.P. 113; includes checklist, slide list, diagrams of layout, order and requisition forms (Box 6, Folder II.B.86)
    - Useful Objects of Good Design, 1951-1954; E.P. 63A; includes loan correspondence, catalogue to Good Design[MoMA Exh. #463, November 21, 1950-January 28, 1951] (Box 7, Folder II.B.87)
    - Uses of the Past, 1964-1972; E.P. 128B; includes edited caption text (Box 7, Folder II.B.88)
    - Visual Language, 1960, 1970; E.P. 107; includes order and requisition forms (Box 7, Folder II.B.89)
    - Ways of Looking[MoMA Exh. #974, July 28-November 1, 1971], 1971-1972; Includes exhibition checklist (Box 7, Folder II.B.90)
    - What Has Happened to the Roman Letter?, 1971; E.P. 131A, 131B; includes checklist, order and requisition forms (Box 7, Folder II.B.91)
    - What is American Painting, Creative Photography, Look at Your Neighborhood, Elements of Design, 1960, undated; Includes checklists, order and requisition forms (Box 7, Folder II.B.92)
    - What Makes a House Modern?, 1954-1955; E.P. 88A, 88B, V.P. 29; includes checklist (Box 7, Folder II.B.93)
    - What the Modern Artist Paints, 1954; E.P. 89; includes checklist, caption text, labels (Box 7, Folder II.B.94)
- Series III. Art Education at MoMA, 1920s-1982 (bulk 1944-1968)
  This series documents the variety of art classes for families, children, seniors, and teachers held at MoMA during D'Amico's tenure. It includes predominantly photographs of class participants and their work, as well as announcements and programs of classes, text and images used for slide talks presented at MoMA and elsewhere, and recorded presentations.
  In 1944, D'Amico initiated the Museum's War Veterans' Art Center, a project that became the People's Art Center in 1948. The Center's classes moved in 1951 to the second and third floors of 21 West 53rd Street. As part of architect Philip Johnson's redesign of the Museum, completed in 1964, D'Amico designed classrooms, furniture, and equipment for new spaces in the Museum's east wing.
  In 1960, D'Amico became President and Director of the Institute of Modern Art, a separate non-profit organization that assumed responsibility for the Museum's school program and other educational activities until his retirement in 1969, when classes for individual students were discontinued.
  Administrative material pertaining to the Department of Education has been moved to Series I. Department of Education Administrative. For classes taught at the Art Barge see Series V. Art Barge; for programs for New York City public high schools see Series II. New York City Public High Schools Program; for publications of the War Veterans' Art Center, see Series VII. MoMA Publications.
  Images depicting student artwork, which do not either relate to specific programs or show students at work, have been transferred to the Department of Education for internal use.
  The series is organized into three subseries:
  Subseries III.A. War Veterans' Art Center,1944-1949
  Subseries III.B. Slide Talks,1943-1960s
  Subseries III.C. Art Classes General,1920s-1982 (bulk 1941-1970)
  - Subseries III.A. War Veterans' Art Center, 1944-1949
    The War Veterans' Art Center was established in 1944 at the suggestion of MoMA trustees Mrs. John D. (Abby Aldrich) Rockefeller, Jr., and Stephen Clark, who both supported it financially. Housed initially in a loft across from the Museum at 681 Fifth Avenue, the Center provided classes in painting, sculpture, ceramics, jewelry, printing, and woodworking to almost 1,500 veterans in its four years of existence. The War Veterans' Art Center was succeeded by the People's Art Center in 1948.
    - Design workshop class, 1944-1947; Photographs of objects: mounted b/w prints previously removed from post album (Box 7, Folder III.A.1)
    - D'Amico interviewing a veteran; instructor Mervin Jules with student, [1944-1948]; B/w prints (Box 7, Folder III.A.2)
    - Finished objects from painting and sculpture classes, [1944-1948]; B/w prints (Box 7, Folder III.A.3)